Georgi Mikhailov Collection 1991.0058
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Georgi Mikhailov Collection
undated, 1982-1987.
1991.0058
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.5 Linear feet
Correspondence, newspaper and magazine clippings regarding Georgi Mikhailov’s life, in particular his time spent as a political prisoner in Soviet labor camps in Northeastern Siberia from 1980-1983. The collection also contains photographs and negatives of Mikhailov and the labor camps.
Mikhailov, Georgi, 1945-
Biography
Georgi N. Mikhailov, born in 1945, was a physics professor at the University of Leningrad. In 1975, he began hosting an open house in his apartment on Sundays which exhibited works of art which had been banned by the Soviet government. The Soviet police force, the K.G.B., searched his apartment in 1977 confiscated 5,000 slides of paintings, which resulted in his dismissal from the University of Leningrad. In February 1979, Mikhailov was arrested and jailed in Leningrad. 300 of his paintings were destroyed at this time. The chapter of Amnesty International in Munich, Germany began advocating for his release. Mikhailov remained in prison in Leningrad for a year before being sent to three Soviet labor camps in Northeastern Siberia between 1980 and 1983 as a political prisoner. He maintained a camera while in the camp and smuggled the negatives to his mother in Leningrad. After being released in 1983, Mikhailov was rearrested two years later and jailed in Leningrad. After his release, he was granted a visa to immigrate to France, and married a French woman, Veronique, in 1985. In 1987, Mikhailov taught a summer course at the Tolstoy Foundation in New York. The collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections by Lawrence Tobin, a personal friend of Mikhailov.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, clippings, and photographic materials regarding Mikhailov's experiences in Soviet Labor camps in Northeast Siberia from 1980-1983. The newspaper and magazine clippings are mostly from 1987, which corresponded with an article in the New York Times regarding Mikhailov’s photographs and labor camp experiences.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence, Clippings, and Photographic Materials (1982-1987, undated) consists of correspondence in Russian, newspaper and magazine clippings in English, German, Japanese, and Russian, as well as black and white photographs, color photographs, and negatives.
Acquisition Information
The Georgi Mikhailov Collection was donated in 1988 by Lawrence and Elizabeth Tobin. Additions to the collection were received in 1989, 1991, and 1993.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to human rights, as well as a large collection of Communist newspapers and publications. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Tobin, Lawrence; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Labor camps.; Negatives.; Photographs.; Political prisoners.; Soviet Union.
- Correspondence, Russian, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fonds Der Freien Russichen Gegenwartskunst, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings, English, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings, German, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings, Japanese, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings, Russian, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs, Black and White, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Color, undated (1982-1983] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Georgi Mikhailov, undated [1982-1983] (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs, Negatives, undated [1982-1983] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, clippings, publication, undated, 1987-2005 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  [Subjects include: 15 8 x 10 B&W and sepia (originals possibly color) photographic prints; Life article, 1987; Photocopy of New York Times article 1987; 2 publications (Russian/German) of exhibition.]